been studying working on
um for for years this is as uh
what like maybe five years ago when we
when we met
four four or five years ago when we met
i knew you were thinking about
sense making and rebuilding
civilizations and
i'm curious um you know i've had the
pleasure of just
kind of being around you for years
what's the best way to
to tell probably a new audience about
your work
i feel like
yeah i'm wondering i'm wondering your
favorite way to explain that
um i know that i
have a favorite way to explain it but uh
i'll jump in if
i'll give my perspective but i'd love to
hear uh what if you have a
shock kind of just a brief narrative
from the beginning
is uh i was homeschooled growing up so
i got to kind of make my own curriculum
which was fortunate
uh and a lot of it had to do with
activism my mom was big into activism so
i got into
environmental work and animal rights
work and social justice issues young
and my dad was into
lots of areas of science and engineering
and philosophy so i was
getting to have that braid of topics
and as i was
um exploring activism one of the things
that i
found was how profoundly interconnected
the problems were and how
the solutions weren't adequately
addressing them and this started showing
up
all over the place in terms of looking
at why are the ecological issues
advancing and not getting better
despite the huge amount of effort
happening in the nonprofit space and
government for benefit
space what is fundamentally inadequate
about the nature of the solution i
remember
being 13 working on helping some project
that was in
kenya protecting elephants from poaching
in an area that was already protected
that the poachers could get in
and so i was 13 so i was just in the u.s
like going door-to-door raising money
and writing letters and
uh but there the people who were there
on the ground were having their
life threatened by the poaching groups
and
the solution was bigger fences around
the preserve so poachers couldn't get in
and legislation in the country for
harsher sentencing for
poachers and the solution after a couple
years of like blood sweat and tears
finally worked
but it didn't address the poverty of the
people that were poaching
and the fact that you know they were in
parts of the world where
uh you know 25 000 kids are starving to
death a day
it didn't address black markets on
animal products it didn't address
mindsets towards animals it didn't
address a macro economy that creates
poverty at scale and you know ships it
to the third world it didn't address any
of those issues
so the same poaching groups moved and
started hunting both the mountain
gorilla and the white rhino more than
they had been both of which were more
endangered and i got to see this because
i wasn't just
looking at one issue i was working with
enough groups that i got to see that
those were connected
and so the tremendously hard and well
motivated work
solved one problem but actually moved
the underlying problem space
to show up in areas that were even more
sensitive and that's really devastating
because the only kind of hope
that i had to deal with the devastation
of the nature of the problems was that
something could be done about it and so
uh fortunately i was also
studying not just all the different
areas of science that i could but
a system of science and bucky fuller's
work and capra's work and kind of how do
how do all the things fit together
and so i started looking at activism
from that lens
and saying
how can we understand the nature of the
problems well enough that we can come up
with solutions that solve that problem
but also don't externalize harm
elsewhere and that required starting to
get into economics and the nature of
why did this perverse incentive arise
and what would it take to internalize
perverse incentive and externality
and the nature of governance systems and
culture and basically civilization writ
large
so then that led to saying okay well
there's a lot of
there's a lot of things that we can say
are getting better you can listen to
hans rosling or
stephen pinker and you know pick things
that are getting better but
you can also look at most
environmentalists or people studying
existential risk and look at things
getting worse and
both are the case there are some metrics
getting better there are some getting
worse that's a destabilization of the
overall space but the things that are
getting worse
are leading to catastrophic tipping
points that will
break the substrate that allows the
things that are getting better to matter
though i start forecasting uh how
long do we have on the various things
and started reading
limits of growth by club of rome and uh
all of the different kind of forecasts
as well as studying civilizational
collapse theory
uh tainter and baudrillard and you know
things like that
how because it becomes pretty clear when
you study history that all of the great
empires that lived for hundreds or
thousands of years
don't still exist whether it's i'm
curious how old are you when
when you're just you're diving into this
uh inquiry is just so fascinated that
you're
you're you're so interested and have
the dedication to dive into this when
when does this occur in your life
i mean this kind of the threat of my
whole life just progressively deeper
inside the prospects you know if you
spend
if you spend time talking with kids
where you listen
and then actually give them space for
the questions to emerge
uh the dedication is there like
they'll i do nature walks with kids
and they want to ask around about
how do trees suck up water and how how
does the light thing work and how do all
the animals and everything interact and
very deep questions they want to know
why the sky is blue
which actually requires understanding
things about optics and about
astronomy and about the sun about
astrophysics and
you know as well as like the nature of
consciousness what is the subjective
experience of blue
and school just doesn't do a great job
of
actually facilitating that curiosity and
so if we force people to be interested
in they aren't interested in
and don't facilitate their interests and
the things they're actually interested
in we kind of break their interest and
they want to
use some hypernormal stimuli um
so i was just fortunate that the things
that were interesting to me i got to pay
attention to
and i think anyone that gets to continue
to pay attention to the things they're
interested in
learns but they also double down on
their own interests
so the things i'm describing now were a
lot of my kind of teenage focus
and uh
and so i started looking at you know
forecasting and civilizational collapse
models anything from
environmental collapse from
overfishing and you know peak resource
utilization to pollution issues to
you know climate type issues as well as
what are the things that lead to
large-scale war
and infrastructure collapse and
those types of things and um
that led to recognizing that as
our technology exponentiates and the
power of our choices exponentiate
but our quality of choice making is not
getting commensurately better to the
power of our choice making
we're having more and more different
escalation pathways to catastrophic risk
globally
and higher and higher probability of
them where
if we try to think about like biotech
risks or nanotech risks or ai mediated
risk or
large-scale war grid collapse if we
tried to solve any of them on their own
they're almost all impossible
to solve and there's too many of them so
i started thinking about what is driving
all of them
why are humans coordinating at scale in
a way that uses
our technological power in ways that
either directly
through conflict theory cause problems
war
and you know war and
exploitation that is known or through
mistake theory cause problems unintended
externalities
and a lot of it is that right like i
don't think the people when they were
making
facebook knew that it would destroy the
entire information ecology but it did so
that's very
nation theoretic issue so we started
thinking about
are there is there some set of
underlying dynamics that give
rise to how humans are coordinating that
are what gives rise to all these
problems the generator functions of them
and to just start to think about like
perverse incentive as long as
uh military industrial complex is one of
the largest blocks of the global economy
and war is profitable and you have uh
the capacity for the supply side to
manufacture artificial demand
can you have a for-profit
military-industrial complex that the
entire global economy depends upon and
lasting peace in a supply and demand
equation
well no so we have to deal with perverse
incentive there that's one example we
can see it in healthcare and we
can see it in mining and we can see it
everywhere and so
you start looking at is the nature of
the incentive system
the economic system where 50 to 100
trillion dollars a day of human activity
moves
but is either directly causing harm or
indirectly causing externality
could we shift that in a way where that
incentive system what
what was in the incentive of an
individual or a corporation or a
nation was in the ins was in the well
aligned with the well-being of the whole
better
right so these were the questions i was
asking trying to study
the austrian school and straight kind of
laissez-faire
approaches or socialist approaches or
marxist approaches or like
techno-optimist
automate everything approaches and i got
to see that there were strengths and
weaknesses of a lot of them and none of
them were actually adequate to space
so put together some research groups
that were working on
understanding the space the generator
functions of catastrophic risk well
enough to say
is there an is there a
categorical set of solutions to the
underlying dynamics of
how humanity coordinates effectively
that is the kernel of a new civilization
model
and that when we study civilizational
decay of what
made rome fall and egypt and the aztecs
and the mayans and et cetera
that if we understand the dynamics that
give rise to civilizational collapse
can we have something that really
addresses all of those dynamics and
addresses
all of the uh escalation pathways to the
catastrophic risks we can see
so so it sounds like almost
correct me if i'm wrong but maybe a
simple way to put that is
if you were to redesign civilization
from scratch
how would you do it is that is that it's
almost
the frame of like well everything that
we've done
has these strengths and weaknesses what
would we do if we do it again from
scratch is that is that
kind of where you're coming from here
well this is a valuable question and
it's an insufficient question and i
spent a lot of
time i was young asking it without
recognizing
uh the enactment problem okay so
sure we actually get there in
factoring that that seems
that all the people are conditioned
currently who are in power in a way that
would resist that and it seems to be not
in the immediate best interest of the
game theoretic
environment so yes it's an important
thought experiment if we were going to
redesign simply say
scratch how would we how do we think the
best run planet would run
uh most enlightened planet would be then
we have
in the current scenario what is actually
a viable path
there and some degree you reverse
engineer from the idea of a future state
to some degree
forward engineer how can we be vectoring
in the right direction and increasing
our capacity to continue to vector in
the right direction
so what i'm hearing is
great thought experiment hey google
lights on
that's not uh eugene do you mind muting
yourself
although it's a great thought experiment
change
just doesn't start we can't just hit a
button and then and then redesign you're
saying
cool great thought experience to have
that vision to think about what is that
beautiful thing
um and
changes changes evolution
change is it's a it's messy
right to actually get to that vision we
actually have to start with where we are
yeah so where are we and where do we
where do you see us actually being able
to go from where we are
so i'll try to bridge this
to some of what wade was talking about
talking about the unraveling
of the american
empire i think we can look at
and i don't claim to be representing his
views accurately here
but just kind of piggyback on some of
the thoughts
we can look at the
united states system and say is it
undergoing civilization
civilizational decay in the way that led
to
the breakdown of previous civilizations
and what would the signs of that be what
kind of
things can we look for we can also look
at the global system that the world has
actually run on since world war
ii that has been us-based and it's very
important to look at these together
from the u.s perspective we can
you know one just kind of quick
insightful thing is that throughout
history democracies or republics systems
of participatory
governance that were at scale not like
small tribal scales
never made it to 300 years right they
have a fairly short life cycle all
uh empires died but some of the dynastic
ones made it a thousand years
and the ones that were more
participatory governance systems lasted
less long the us is at around 250 years
depending upon
you know exactly the start date you pick
so this is the time cycle factoring
history of
the the adequate decay of a
republican to understand why
there's a bunch of reasons why uh and i
won't get into all of them but
the people who are willing to fight a
revolutionary war to
make something happen right if they
lived in the direct experience of
tyranny of government and where they
were
willing to die rather than let
themselves be governed in a way that
felt tyrannical
then they're also so willing to do the
extraordinarily hard work of
participatory governance
which means show up at the town hall not
let just let somebody else make the
decisions
read all the papers be actively informed
about what's going on
so that you can participate in
governance because you have the direct
experience of how terrible not
being involved in your own governances
but as time goes on and several
generations pass and that just becomes a
myth that no one has any embodied
experience of
and there's like mortgages to pay and
stuff on tv and to do
um i don't even want to go to jury duty
let alone be really actively informed
and engaged in participatory governance
so if the people
stop checking the state and it's no
longer truly a governance of foreign by
the people then the state stops being
able to do what it's supposed to do
which is check the predatory aspects of
the market
i'll i'll just make this frame because
that's an important frame
absolutely i love it one way
thinking about all of the problems in
the world is that they're all
coordination problems
um that it's patterns of human behavior
at scale that cause them
and it needs to be different patterns of
human behavior at scale to solve them
and so how do we get lots of people to
coordinate their behavior when they want
different things and they have different
understandings of the world and
different world views in ways that lead
to
better solutions for the individual
groups and the whole
overall it's a hard thing when the
churchill said about democracy and the
founding fathers here said something
similar
that democracy is the single worst form
of government ever created
saved for all the other forms what they
meant is the idea of governance that you
get a lot of different people to
actually participate together is just a
really hard proposition
and it's why if you look at you know
human history until
like the thing we call civilization only
started 10
10 13 000 years ago but we have 200
or 300 000 years of sapien existence of
people that were genetically and
neurologically similar to us
and those groups never got beyond give
or take what's called the
dunbar number 150 people in a tribe and
it's like why was that such a hard upper
bound why
did for hundreds of thousands of years
humans never make groups bigger than
that
and it's actually like the
the simplest way i think of it is uh it
had to do with limits of coordination
so communication and coordination if the
tribe
has to make a decision that's very
consequential to move or not or to
change some deep aspect of how they do
things
up to about that size everyone can
participate
in a tribal council and all have a say
in what the rest of their life is going
to be subject to
but as soon as you start getting more
people than that everyone can't actually
have a say because you can't just
you can't have time to listen to a
thousand people right
it would take a month to make a decision
on anything and no one
would even have the work memory to hold
it and so then
i'm have to rep pick representatives to
make
choices on my behalf now my life is
subject to choices
that i don't have a say in no i'd rather
cleave and make my own smaller group and
be more self-determined
and so the denmark number was a limit of
how and up to that size i could talk to
everyone and get their sense made
things so i didn't just have it's like
an anonymous the right or the left over
there that i could just have a
pejorative straw man version of i had
people that i knew intimately
so um that's
almost all of evolutionary history now
when the tribe would get as big as it
could get then it would cleave and
some of the people would move somewhere
else lots of migration happened until
eventually
population keeps growing we've migrated
everywhere that we can now population
keeps growing and tribal warfare becomes
pressed right because now we're
competing for scarce resource
now there's a basis to have tribes unify
against larger external tribes and we
call that kind of the beginning of
civilization
which means it was in a war game
theoretic kind of context
and so now we unify together and try to
create government structures for these
larger numbers of people because we have
to
and so there's binding energy to hold
the cleaving energy
associated with an enemy hypothesis um
so cajun
sure so when i think of coordination
it feels like it's still related to
connection
and and if if you want to take it
further maybe empathy
right when when people don't have
a sense of each other or where they're
at
or what the pain and
problem is
people don't really care like you know
if you know i really care about
something
daniel and you might be like oh you
should meet this person and that could
change my life
right you might you might give me 10
minutes you might give me an hour you
you might help but
it feels like it starts that
coordination starts with
some sort of connection um
yeah that came up for me so it's a nice
feel
uh i mean there definitely needs to be
some fealty
and it's a nice idea that it emerges
from empathy it doesn't have to emerge
from empathy it can emerge
from a shared enemy which it often does
and so then there's fealty to each other
not because we necessarily care about
each other but because we care about
ourselves and our sub
in group and we feel that we have to be
bound with them against whoever the out
group is
but yeah the dunbar number was partly a
limit on
how many relationships i could deeply
track
and i'm willing to make certain
sacrifices of what i want most for
people i really know and love and i've
known forever and i see every day and
they know me
it's much harder to make sacrifices for
anonymous people
that i have no idea who they are that
are somewhere else right
and um so as you get
beyond that you have to have a shared
religion or patriotism or some kind of a
group identity that everyone gets to be
part of so that they
i they identify with each other through
shared group identity
right we can see that in the us that has
broke down where there's very little
sense of what it means to be a
u.s citizen that everyone's on the same
page with it really creates binding
energy there's much more of a sense of
what it means to be on the left or the
right
it has so much enmity towards each other
that the thinking as a whole
doesn't have something like shared
nationalism or patriotism and that's
part of the issue
i guess so fundamentally
do we do humans just need
pain or an enemy need to really come
together
in and coordinate in a in a larger way
at scale
it's a good question and i think i'll
better be able to answer it if we go
back to the train it was on about
coordination
so if we look at all of the issues we
want
all this coordination issues because we
say well no climate change not a
coordination issue it's a
straightforward environmental issue
we've got to do certain things with
the uh transportation
and the energy sector or whatever no
it's a coordination issue because you
have to have enough people that have a
shared
world view around what is true what is
real what the problem is that they can
come up with adequate solutions
and that a major chunk of humanity isn't
fighting against them to keep it from
happening
because they have a different worldview
or different assessment right
and let's say that your solution
involves whatever some kind of carbon
tax or something that
countries have to agree to and uh
agreement without enforcement ends up
being a very tricky thing and how do you
do enforcement internationally
um with superpowers that have nukes so
let's say
that the u.s and europe were to agree to
some kind of taxation policy which
decreased their near-term gdp growth but
was good for the environment long-term
and we don't
all say well that makes sense but then
let's say china doesn't and we have a
concern about china seeking to be a
global dominant empire and if we can't
enforce them to because
does that what enforcement mechanisms
are we going to use that don't
create war then does that just basically
and that increased gdp and that be that
they have relative to everyone else
equals
increased globalization and military
powers are we just
ceding the control of the world to china
like that's a very real set of theory of
trade-off
considerations so your assessment of
climate change can't be separate from
your assessment
of geopolitics and underlying economics
and so
we don't assess the problems in a deep
enough interconnected enough way to come
up with good solutions
and we don't have enough uh shared sense
making
that enough of the world wants to do the
same things right so
we can what do you mean by what do you
what do you mean by specific what's that
mean
what is actually real
is climate change at all right so if you
talk to some environmentalists like very
good ones like lovelock
it's not only real but it's already too
late there's nothing we can do about it
and
the earth will become uninhabitable uh
other people say it's a very serious
thing it's
on its way to that but we still have
time there are other people that think
that it's a real thing but it's not that
serious the earth changes
will migrate and there are other people
think it's utter hoax right
sense making have we been able to make
sense of the world that we live in well
enough to inform what we think are right
choices
so when we think about democracy
what we're talking about is a collective
choice making system how do we
not just make choice me as an individual
in my family or an individual economic
actor choosing to buy or sell something
but we're going to share roads we're
going to share defense we're going to
decide that it does make sense to start
that war
or not so in autocracy
we just basically the power is ceded to
whoever it is that's going to make that
choice but in a participatory governance
we're supposed to
participate to do collective choice
making the basis of choice making
collective choice making is collective
sense making about what we think is
actually happening
and sense making about what we think the
effect of a particular
injunction might be and meaning making
what do we think is important
that we're in service to and
communication
our ability to converse effectively
enough with each other that we can get
on the same page about this so that we
can
do collective choice making so voice
making has as its antecedents
sense making as its prerequisites sense
making meaning making
and communication and just to jump into
sense making i
you're reminding me of uh
thinking of an ecology right and and
there's usually a keystone species of
that you could kind of like point out
that and be like for example in colombia
the jaguar the jaguars health is great
the amazon's good if it's if it's not
amazon's bad right
it's a very simple way so if we think of
sentence making as
a term you you mentioned earlier which
is beautiful in
information ecology where you take this
information ecology and make sense of it
how is is there something as simple as a
keystone species where you could just be
like
yeah we're that the health of our sense
making right now
it's it's fundamentally
on the decline it's not healthy um
is there is there something that we can
point out that or or many things that we
can point out where we're like
guys our sense making abilities often
and in this model you described
it's it's almost like the reminds me of
the the story of the
the princess and the p right this
she's she's sleeping on a piece she's so
sensitive
that if a pee is under her bed it
affects her
right and so there's this
[Music]
almost a butterfly effect a better
better
approach of if if this is off
right how can we show people that this
is off or that it's not
i think that would should be a helpful
place for us to start
[Music]
so i appreciate that as i'm sharing
things individual things i'm saying
are sparking in interest and you're
wanting to go
down those um avenues but i also noticed
that about
six strands of bin which would actually
be necessary to close to do a good job
of this
looking at things in a more
interconnected way means the chunk size
is a little harder
and that's the important thing for
people to understand is that
you can't fit a good assessment of
anything into a tweet
or into a short news bite so an
attention span forgive me
when attention spent through downtown
you become a worse sense maker for sure
because you
you have to compress the complexity of
reality into something that will fit
into the tiny attention
and so actually expanding attention to
be able to hold
multiple views multiple epistemologies
all of the relevant things
so that you can then come up with a
solution that's actually adequate as
is requisite so i
uh i have heard the is there a butterfly
effect to affect sense making
let me try to close a couple of loops
that maybe we'll bring it together
so we want to improve human coordination
we want to improve our sense making
where we all are better at having
the capability of doing assessment of
what is actually
true base reality and you can see in the
us right now
hydroxychloroquine is a wonder drug it's
an utter false
forest that actually kills more people
if they use it uh
masks really help masks make it worse
systemic racism is this
most critical issue in the nation
systemic racism isn't even a thing in
police violence violence when
statistically corrected
is worse for white people uh
on and on right um
china is trying to become a globally
dominant empire
it's very close or they're not like
there's
maximally polarized views around
just base reality because these aren't
these aren't values these are is this is
something true
right so clearly we are not doing a good
job
at collective sensement um so when we
say we want to get collective
coordination we want to get our ability
for
for everyone to actually know what is
true empirically well
for us to be able to identify what
values we're trying to serve and be able
to hear the value someone else is trying
to serve and say is
are there better strategies that can
serve these simultaneously
maybe i care about the environment here
maybe you care about
your kids being able to get good jobs
and there's a particular proposition
that's crafted in a way where if it goes
through your kids get good jobs and the
environments
and vice versa so i have to pretend like
i don't arab kids getting good jobs you
have to pretend like you don't care
about the environment because the
proposition is based on that theory
of trade-offs and i've now collapsed my
values into a strategy to achieve them
but if i said wait wait
i care about this you care about that is
there a better proposition we can come
up with
for what could achieve both both of them
so we separate the value from the
strategy to
achieve it you can see that it almost
seems mind-boggling
it's bogglingly ridiculous that we have
a
democracy where you vote on a
proposition where you weren't
involved in crafting what is a good
proposition so some
special interest group that has a very
narrow interest
puts forward a proposition and markets
it to a group of people where it's
directly beneficial to them and this is
why almost every
proposition gets about half the vote yes
and have to vote no
which also means that it inherently
polarizes the population which is
why democracies die younger one of the
main reasons
is it's actually very hard to get lots
of people to coordinate it's very easy
to have one person rule or a small
number of people rule
and if you're creating a voting system
where the people
people aren't doing good proposition
creation first it is necessarily
polarizing
because the thing that you're voting for
seems like it's actively trying to harm
what is meaningful and sacred to me and
vice versa
so um
since the beginning of the thing we call
civilization
very few total people have lived in
democracies or republics
almost everybody has lived in feudalism
or autocracy of some kind democracies
have
emerged just a few times in rare little
pockets
and when they've emerged they have
emerged following
periods of cultural enlightenment this
is a really key insight the cultural
enlightenment because it's gonna come to
your butterfly effect
yeah so the athenian democracy
with all of its flaws still a movement
in the direction of more participatory
governance
emerged out of a kind of
greek enlightenment that valued
everyone's ability to do better sense
making so let's really value
education and the development of the
individual so everyone should learn
history and formal logic and grammar and
um rhetoric and etc so they can all
actually make sense of base reality on
their own and make good choices
and then they all also need the socratic
method which means that they can argue
any point they can take other people's
perspective well
and you can see how profoundly broken
down that capacity and that value and
orientation currently is
if you have a bunch of people that can
make sense of reality directly on their
own not listen to what some authorities
said and decide
which of the authorities they listen to
but direct empirical capacity
and then they can take each other's
perspective those people can have a
conversation that will end up
resulting in some ability for effective
compromise and
movement forward but if the capacity for
sense-making conversation breaks down
then
the basis that gave rise to the
democracy republic being able to emerge
breaks down
and so we can see that in the u.s the
u.s came out of the european
enlightenment
where there was this kind of renaissance
idea you don't just have to be a
specialist at one thing you can have a
deep
background in lots of things
science we can actually empirically all
get a good base understanding of reality
and the hegelian dialectic will always
seek for any thesis
an antithesis and then a higher order
synthesis can we take multiple
perspectives
and try to find higher order
reconciliation
that the underlying public education and
fourth estate or news that are required
for people to all be
developed in their capacity to make make
sense of the world and participate in
governance
and to know what's going on have went
through enough institutional decay that
nobody really has a sense of what's
going on or to the degree they do
they're outraged and certain about
things that
half the population thinks that they're
desperately wrong about right that
they're outraged and certain about
uh so we can look at this as the
collapse of the american
empire because you don't have the
ability for a real republic because you
don't have participatory governments
because the prerequisites aren't there
so look at it in a bigger way which is
we can
and this will then wrap up we can look
at
at the breakdown of the rope the first
ever globalized world order that has
been since world war ii
because of course empires got larger as
time went on and there was a game
theoretic competition for more size
british empire was not quite a world
ruling empire
um but after world war ii
it was the first time that we could
never have a war again between the major
empires we
always had war between major empires but
they never had a nuke they never had
utterly catastrophic tech that made a
war that no one
could win and so after world war
ii we had to do something unprecedented
and say how do we
never have a war between the major
parties again and so
we said well we have to be so
economically interdependent that it's
never advantageous to bomb each other
because
it is better to coordinate with each
other and so let's do globalization
and have supply chains that interconnect
us in such a way
that we don't survive without import and
export
well in a way that made sense right and
we had proxy wars but we didn't have
major wars
from until now but it also created
one glo global civilization really
because none of the nations really can
operate on their own
a global civilization mediated by
globalism that is profoundly fragile
where breakdown you know a virus in one
part of the world can become a virus in
the entire world can start breaking
down supply chains breaking down social
fabric within countries between
countries
and so covid was just a big enough thing
to show the systemic fragility
and the systemic fragility that's been
cascading is really like the second and
third order effects are really
just starting to show up and we'll
continue for some time
and obviously when we look at the social
tension that has
that arose with george floyd it was a
long-term issue
but after a tremendous amount of
unemployment of course there's going to
be more likelihood for violence in the
street
when people's fundamental needs aren't
met you always get more
willingness for violence and so
even that was one of the secondary
effects of
coveted type effects so what we're
experiencing right now also is that the
globalized world order
that the kind of bretton woods
agreements put in place
are breaking down or almost totally
broken u.s has pulled out of nato at who
decreased the u.n and the major empires
the the biggest countries in the world
are doing cyber attacks on each other
and espionage and they know it so it's
not
following peacetime agreements it's
basically unconventional war rather than
conventional kinetic war
but it can all right hang tight and
conveniently getting uh
so we have a breakdown of the global
order and we have a breakdown of a
country
and uh leading the global order
simultaneously
and then we have a very big question of
so what happens now uh wade davis do we
have together
increasing chaos facilitated by
population reduction catastrophic risk
we're at large
do we have china
to build trains all around the world and
ports and whatever and they run the
world and
what does that look like or at the end
of where the the u.s
has decayed to can we reboot something
like a meaningful
participatory governance if you were to
want to reboot
it you have to drive a cultural
enlightenment that is
the prerequisite this is the butterfly
is the high value on
everyone's capacity to do much better
sense making
and much higher quality conversation so
they can participate
i think this is the exact conversation i
want
you and wade
to to kind of discuss and digest and
that was um
that was beautiful thank you
um yeah do you how are you feeling do
you want to take a
take a breath how about we all take a
breath and then we'll we'll come back
with weight
sure okay great i i think we're
it's almost like you've opened the
connection
of of where both of you really really
fit in together and
i think now the audience gets both of
you
really well where you're coming from
and i'm excited
[Music]
really really fit in together and i
think
now the audience gets both of you really
well
where you're coming from and i'm excited
[Music]
really really fit in together and i
think
now the audience gets both of you really
well
where you're coming from and i'm excited
[Music]
hey everyone keep uh keep hanging out
for a sec we're trying this uh this new
thing where we uh beam the zoom call
onto the inside of the playa alchemist
uh pyramid here
uh we'll get it straightened out in just
a moment really
really fitting together and um i think
now the audience gets both of you really
well
where you're coming from and i'm excited
[Music]
really really fit in together and i
think
now the audience gets both of you really
well
where you're coming from and i'm excited
[Music]
really really fit in together and i
think
now the audience gets both of you really
well
where you're coming from um and i'm
excited
to bring us all together and see uh
let's do what emerges
all of us thank you too for being here
this feels like such a poignant
conversation this time
from what i find interesting about the
two of you
is that you guys are pointing at i think
something very similar
you're stumbling on it in two different
ways
you're coming at it from two different
angles wade
cultural anthropologist storyteller
and and you wrote this article you
you shared with me and so forth expanded
just you just feel like something had to
be said
yeah i mean i just was going to say that
you know
you introduced me to daniel when we
first connected and uh i just loved
listening to him
and uh when i was just listening to the
your conversation
it struck me that uh just how important
it is to know history
you know um if you
i was just reading earlier today one of
the classic
um books uh about vietnam
by stanley karnoff and and you know you
just you just see how those
those those men you know robert mcnamara
and you know dean rusk and and johnson
and
and all all their kind of various
advisors the scores of them were just
stumbling around
in that void doing what they tried to do
and
and and it's almost agonizing to to
be reading the contemporary accounts of
their decision making in 1963 to four to
five
knowing what was going to be the result
and
and uh the the the kind of analysis that
daniel just did
taking us through the patterns of
history you know if
you know he quoted churchill and another
one of
i think churchill's saying i think it
was churchill who said
that you know if you don't know if you
don't study history you'll never
um you know you'll it'll um
uh you're condemned to repeat the same
mistakes over and over and over
and you know in in my little analysis
the covet thing
what made it i suppose unique and
certainly what caused it to
hit a nerve it's just the point of view
you know the kind of the anthropological
lens that i was thinking of this less as
a story of medicine
than of culture and but but daniel takes
us to a whole another level of depth
right
and and
and it raises the issue of how
astonishing
the important knowledge of history is
for anyone
who who has the audacity to think that
they can
lead us or lead anyone right and
and when you it's not trivial um
you know that george patton knew
classical
uh warfare of of the greeks and the
metropolitan you know the
mediterranean zone it's not an accident
that churchill won the nobel prize for
literature
and wrote more books than most
contemporary politicians have read
and when you think of the most
horrifying
aspect of many horrifying aspects
of the of the current administration in
washington
it was you know the word ignorant is is
really means without knowledge lack of
gnosis right
and and when you have a president who
literally doesn't know when world war
ii began you know who doesn't know
um the most fundamental aspects of
history
who who has never read anything who
famously doesn't read
and then when you you contrast that to
what we just heard from daniel you know
um unraveling the threads
of history the mystic connections of
history
that have brought us to where we are it
just my overwhelming impression
listening to him is just
how important how vital a knowledge of
his
history is um in the moment
and certainly for those who who have the
um the gumption and and the audacity
to believe that they have the right to
lead the rest of us
and interesting as you're saying that i
was thinking about what you were
speaking of of is this asian century
will it be chinese-led
and xi jinping is a very serious scholar
of history political uh theory
philosophy military history
um my understanding is uh actually a
very
serious translator and scholar of all of
the
kind of classic chinese works um
and that when he came to power the
people who were in high positions of the
ccp
all had to have a pretty high degree of
background
and training in uh the 36 strategies and
the art of war and
warring states region and you can
imagine if
the u.s senate and congress all had to
have
the whole kind of history of western
philosophy in the canon
and the napoleonic wars and alexander
the great and etcetera would be
a different story and kind of the
founding fathers did
it right and this is one of the
institutional things is that
when you when you're trying to emerge
you have to work really hard but there's
a way of kind of getting fat when you
are
the dominant empire and you've forgotten
the problems and the very hard work of
staying actively educated and engaged
doesn't seem immediately
eminently necessary and that's one of
the things that leads to the decay
i think that's so true i mean you know
the famous quick tip by kennedy when he
welcomed all the nobel laureates to the
white house and he said there wasn't as
much
in intellectual firepower in that room
since the last time thomas jefferson
died alone
and i think that's so true i mean i you
know there's a
there's an understandable but a kind of
a disturbing
american almost embrace of ignorance you
know
there's a you know if you if you know
too much you're sort of
you know you're not really a man or
something uh there there's a
there's a there's a cert certainly we're
we're
um you know until 9 11 the vast majority
of congressmen didn't even
own passports and one of the one of the
things that i've note
besid um uh lecture on private jet trips
for the national geographic that would
go around the world
and they were very very expensive trips
for people
and generally the the the individuals
who came along were
really wonderful people very very
affluent by definition
and they had all had incredibly
successful careers but their careers had
focused on
on you know making the most hospital
beds or something or making
them running this corporation and being
a real
expert on packaged meats or something
like that
but outside of that expertise
outside of golf football and sports
there just wasn't it wasn't as if
um a general in for education was deemed
to be that essential to
to corporate affairs i mean i i used to
go through this with my own
father-in-law who was who was very well
read compared to normal politicians but
he was a
a and most beloved man the most
wonderful man the great
greatest the embodiment of everything
that american
a great american is in my opinion but he
was senate foreign relations committee
chairman
uh almost president he was offered the
vice presidency by richard nixon and he
turned it down
i supported rockefeller
and you know yet you know when he came
to visit us at our fish camp in northern
british columbia
guidebook in hand he came over to me and
said
wade did you know canada was the second
biggest country on earth
and uh and then he was very desperate to
have a newspaper and that the nearest
newspaper we could get for him
was a four day old copy of the toronto
globe
and mail it's a bush pilot brought in
and granddaddy's sitting there by the
fire
very very content with the newspaper at
last but then he quizzically
he looks at me pulls down the newspaper
and looks up from his bifocals and said
wait why is there so much news on canada
in this newspaper
and and those are kind of um not
gentle gentle
cliches and uh and obviously granddaddy
at that
point was past his prime so i'm not
being in any
but there is there is this um that
this this this sense that to know too
much is to be
almost suspect in the united united
states and i don't think that was
certainly true
in the kennedy era maybe they thought
they knew too much in the case of
someone like mcnamara but but certainly
you know you know not knowledge of the
world has never been a credential for
political office in the united states
i'll share a couple thoughts on um
partly how i think we got here and it's
by
no means a uh comprehensive addressing
because i there's i think there's
actually quite a few threads that are
involved
what makes someone particularly good in
the market
and what makes them comprehensively
educated about history don't necessarily
overlap all that well
and doing very well in the market means
that you can
influence dc to have people do your
bidding and
the people who are susceptible to do
that will do better and whatever so
there's a whole bunch of
other reasons but a couple reasons that
maybe are slightly less
often thought about and valuable one is
uh i think the focus on in the types of
knowledge that mattered coming out of
world war ii
made a very drastic shift to stem focus
because of the critical role that
technology played in the war
and we can see that it was like we built
the entire manhattan project around
oppenheimer and like a few people who
had
really asymmetric technological and
physical insights
and bletchley park around and you know a
couple major things around touring and
von neumann that pretty much determine
the war right like
the bomb and the computer and so
and then synthetic rub yeah that's
a third example and
and sputnik uh getting there first i
think there was this very real sense
of and one way to look at world war ii
was the competition between the us and
the russians for the german scientists
um and not just you know so operation
paper clip here and the
russian version of it there's the famous
joke that who would win the cold war
between
the ussr and usa was who got the better
nazi scientists um
but like it played a significant role
but
i think there became a very heavy focus
and let's focus on stem but george
washington
said it should be the primary aim of
this
government to train every single citizen
in the science
of government and the science of
government meant history politics game
theory
courtier dynamics etc because if they
didn't understand it
those who did would run everything and
it wouldn't be it would become a
kleptocracy and then an oligarchy or
some weird thing not a democracy
so i think the civics training became
very de-emphasized that's one part
the other part i think is very important
is and this is so i'm gonna i'm gonna
say something that i think is more
sympathetic with the
anti-intellectual movement because i
think the anti-intellectual movement was
a
game theoretic counter strategy to
intellectualism used as a political
weapon
and things can be true that are not
representative of the whole truth right
like
one of the things i see all the time is
people say well obviously
herbs and supplements and peptides don't
really work that well because there
aren't that many phase three clinical
trials showing
that they work and there are four pharma
meds well there's no money
because there's no patentability on any
of those things
of course they'll never get phase three
trials and the phase three trials that
showed that premarin worked or vioxx
work didn't mean that they didn't kill
massive numbers of people because what's
included in the scope of the safety
analysis
and so it's true those pastry clinical
trials are true
and if you are literate you understand
they're true but they're not
representative right because
if here's the whole space of possible
health interventions
the ones that are profitable will get
the most research and they represent
this space so you then the preponderance
of data is an uneven distribution
right so similarly i can put an ipcc
together and say
all of the stuff on climate change but
it doesn't rep but
dc is still running the benign china
hypothesis and not looking at that
particular issue seriously
bannon was actually a big part of you
know and trump delivering the us from
the benign
china hypothesis so there was a way
that i see that throughout history
whenever
something becomes a source of legitimate
authority whether
it's the church or academia then
there's so much power in being the one
who said says what is true
that then anyone who's very good at the
game of power has a maximum incentive to
try to capture
and influence that legitimate authority
so the legitimate authority starts
getting influenced by
who's funding it and how the prestige
networks work and those types of things
so then legitimate authority in the u.s
started to have a particular set of
political biases that a lot of people in
the us didn't feel
represented their interests well and so
but they couldn't argue against the ipcc
thing well
but they could feel like it was not
aligned with their interests so
anti-intellectualism since they couldn't
compete at it was actually their counter
weapon i just won't
engage with the weapons that you're
using that feel like they're against me
and so one of the ways i think
to actually have sense making really be
able to be pervasive
is that it is not weaponized for partial
political or economic
agendas that it is authentically seeking
to understand the entire space and be in
the benefit of everyone as opposed to
that as a virtue signal otherwise i
think the anti-intellectualism becomes a
natural counter weapon
[Music]
let me ask you about china because one
of the things that um
uh it was interesting in the criticism
of my
article um i was i was
a number of people jeffrey sachs for one
a friend of mine who founded code pink
you know quite liberal
individual we're very critical of my
last paragraph when i essentially said
we'll miss the american era
if china is in control and i cited in
that the treatment of the ubers like
the social contracts um social capital
thing and just the treatment of
democracy etc
and uh there's a sort of thing on the
left that we're now
bashing china and i is that the left
being reflexively
countered with whatever trump is doing
because trump's bashing china therefore
we shouldn't pass china
and then you parse it down and you see
that jeffrey sachs is up to his
you know eyeballs in contracts with the
chinese government
um and i know that in my travels around
the world
i've seen the footprint of china
virtually everywhere
i mean just if you can build your way to
the dominance that's what they're doing
i mean
the police station in rortonga the opera
house in dakar
an interchange in togo in in lomme
the capital of togo i mean obviously the
the the
the belt initiative but also great roads
across the amazon
and um and i'm i'm
and i've also of course seen firsthand
and
what has happened to tibet and there
seems to be this thing as
long as china does development work it's
you know there's build stuff
that somehow it's okay and that they're
not you know and that gets back in this
whole thing where genocide is
universally condemned but ethnicity the
destruction of people's life
is not only not condemned is considered
proper development policy
in in many quarters so what is the
what is your sense of china in the next
century
yeah it's such a critical question um
i don't claim to know what's in
xi ji ping's mind or what the internal
plans and sense making of the ccp are
and nor do i represent that whatever
those
are represents the actual will of all
the chinese people outside of beijing
um which it obviously doesn't uh
let me just sort of interrupt daniel but
you're so right in that i mean
there is a terrible tendency in the west
to see china as this monolith
when in fact of course it's remarkably
diverse ethnically
uh vast country vast numbers of people
vast
orientations and so on i'm sorry go
ahead
i'm not going to say that there aren't
some
people who have a xenophobic racist
relationship
just because it seems big and scary and
they don't like the big scary things so
they make it the chinese monolith of
course there is some reactive
non-thinking part of that
i wouldn't say that that is much dumber
than the benign china the hypothesis was
i would say those are kind of equally
not clear assessments
um i think the hundred year marathon is
a particularly interesting book around
china's long-term plan starting in give
or take 1949 and it is kind of tracking
quite well
uh i i think
i think we've had a period where nobody
remembers in their own
lived experience very serious war
in the developed world and so they don't
really have any embodied sense that
that's even a thing so they're
their actual sense of history is quite
bad right like their embodied sense is
quite bad
and so they they don't recognize that
like slavery and
genocide and initiating war and empire
has been kind of the story
for the whole history of civilization
everybody like it's not just been
european white slavery it was the
you know the ottomans and turks
enslaving europeans it was people in
asia
in slavery inter asian slavery it was uh
you know command command g violence with
other
first tribes people like largely humans
have just been kind of violent for
a long time
often and that's an important part of
the story so when we say the us was
built on
genocide and slavery and how can it have
any kind of moral value
that's a very real story and like what
do we do for reparations on genocide and
slavery
and the whole world was in a context
of slavery and genocide arguably you
could say british colonialism was less
violent than dutch or
spanish or some of the other
colonialisms you go to the congo and
whatever
in some ways so this is why the
historical context is important and so
then i'm going to think of china in
light of that
if i put myself in my imagining of xi's
position i'm actually quite empathetic
to everything he's doing
and in some ways i can say it's the
smartest thing anyone in the world is
doing because there are some critical
problems that it appears he's paying
attention to that no one
else is even paying earnest attention to
so i'm very empathetic to the solutions
he has that doesn't mean i like the
solutions or want them to happen
so just to kind of briefly frame that
rule of law requires monopoly of
violence
if you don't have a monopoly of violence
how do you enforce this rule of law
if we say you can't cut down the parks
but the dudes who are cutting down the
trees have bigger guns than the police
do then you can cut down the parks right
well how do you have monopoly of
violence when individuals or small
groups can make
catastrophic weapons that can destroy
whole cities and whatever because
exponential tech makes that possible
where i can get access to crispr gene
drives and
people in their basement can make bio
weapons or
uh you know drones with thermite bombs
that are like easy to make that can take
out massive aspects of infrastructure
this problem of i can do way more damage
with an ar-15 than a knife
but i can do way more damage with a
crisper gene drive than an ar-15
and it was very hard to make nukes i
needed nation state capacity
to make nukes but i don't need
nation-state capacity to
make drone weapons and so we have
an emerging world where decentralized or
cyber weapons that can take out
infrastructure we have a
place where decentralized exponential
tech
makes the world frail in a way that
there's no precedent in all of history
for
this is why we need history and we also
need imagination
right and forecasting um and so
what do we do about that what do we do
when people can in their basement not
just be going crazy and getting an ar-15
with a lot of clips but they can be
building crisper
weapons china's answer is there is no
answer other than ubiquitous
surveillance
you need a bit of surveillance to be
able to suppress a harm that is that
great and the harm of the suppression is
less bad than the harm of doing that
thing
and uh that's
actually kind of understandable right
and
they're also not in the position of
seeing that the the us
as having been as like innocent and
rosie as a lot of people in the u.s do
because from the outside
the predatory debt lending they've been
doing all over the world for the last 20
years
we were doing for a lot longer than that
they just kind of took world bank model
copied it and made it better
um the wars that we waged whatever so
i'm very empathetic to why china is
doing what it's doing and i'm actually
very impressed with its ability to build
high-speed trains all around the world
when we can't fix roads right
um a talk rarely see actually autocracy
with no term limits so you can do 100
year planning with no internal
coordination costs is an amazing system
to build
that said i think if anyone who's
concerned about racism in the us
doesn't look at the chinese treatment of
the uigar
and take very seriously what is its
actual
view towards racial justice like
demonstrably
and if the way we're dealing with it in
the us
is leading to increasing division of the
us which leads to the rapidity of its
breakdown which is ceding the 21st
century to chinese
ai technologically empowered autocracy
with that value system
are we just being short-sighted as
about
actual racism over the next century or
any other issue like that
i think she also has paid attention to
civilizational collapse better because
he also has a longer history right china
has a much longer history
and so he knows that civilizational
collapse happens because you get
overthrown externally
you have internal descent or you run out
of resources so he's worked to have a
hundred year
resource acquisition plan which belton
road and
and pearls and whatever are part of the
sesame credit system
and the iot surveillance system ensures
that internal descent can't happen
and an adequate military ensures that
nobody can be
overthrow them without catastrophic risk
to themselves
but any people should think about how do
i prevent our own people from
going through civilizational collapse so
like i'm simultaneously very empathetic
with and want answers
really better than those answers
well there's another there's another
thing that i think that people in the
west um
fail to understand is just the um the
the reflex for order it goes back to the
whole confucian
um ideology um
and you realize what china has actually
endured
over the last 150 years not just the
humiliation
leading to the boxer rebellion but you
know the great leap forward which led to
48 million people dying of starvation
the chaos of the cultural revolution
what 35 million people died in the civil
war and
world war ii i mean i mean
it's no wonder the chinese citizenry is
perfectly happy with the stability that
the
social
credit system is invoking i mean the
polls say that chinese
people like it because they just want
order
predictability i wouldn't say i could
trust those polls
because of the credit system if there's
a self-reform dynamic
right of course my sense
is from what i have heard of people who
have lived and spent a lot of time
throughout
various regions of china is
that the further you get in
actual miles outside of beijing
the less kind of ccp standard narrative
people hold and it's large enough that
as powerful as the ccp is
it still can't unify one point whatever
it is five
eight billion people we think the
number's probably a lot higher than the
reported number
all that well like that's a that's a
hard thing to do
and this actually one of my concerns is
i
i think the benign china hypothesis of
like no china is just trying to grow its
people they're not trying to become a
world empire
don't worry about it is completely
dreadful
but also chinese or the great bad guys
is the only thing that could unify by
all of china against the west
right because the people who are there
like louis vuitton and they like silicon
valley and they like
hollywood but they won't if the message
they keep hearing is that americans
don't like the chinese
i really want to separate the view of
the chinese from a particular regime
well there's a whole issue of faith and
and uh
um and you know which comes the job
the motherland of the motherland and uh
no that's fascinating i i
you should write a book about this
we've got 23 books
professor then i have none so my best
chance of any of this being in the book
is you and i having conversations
well listen this has been really
wonderful both of you guys i've got a
lot of actually for some family stuff on
labor day weekend but
that's daniel i really want to keep in
touch with you man i just
really enjoyed both this dialogue and um
and our previous one on
the phone so honor to be with you man
thank you so much thank you for your
time thank you for
uh honoring us with your presence and
attention and
and thank you for your work great thanks
so
much genuinely appreciate it okay daniel
thank you bye-bye
um i'm gonna turn my video on and uh
can we turn my video on i would love to
thank everyone
great wow
daniel wade
thank you so much
we here apply alchemist really believe
that was
your viewing points your messages the
work
that you guys have been spending your
lifetimes really being together
is just so important to give voice to in
this moment
so thank you for giving voice to it
thank you for
doing it thank you for being it thank
you for coming together here
in this uh multiverse
culture vultural virtual pyramid
of burning man i want to take a moment
and thank
the entire team that brought this
together i want to thank the builders
the build crew as you can imagine
through that built this pyramid was a
little different than the one that built
last year's pyramid i
was completely amazed with what they
were
able to create if if you're in the
pyramid and you give us some
emoji love that'd be amazing
i want to take thank the co-founders
of this camel right everyone thank you
thank you very much
thank you from all space vr uh thank you
from this
particularly speaking to you right now
thank you again bye drew yunji
thank you for being here this has been a
week of getting to know you guys
to really kind of be in the princess
with y'all
so we're gonna have this one again
reminded me of what burning man's all
about there's still plenty more coming
together there's plenty more to expect
their differences i don't think that's
one of the good things about this
uh thank you all for that sunday is as
you all know
how do you spend all our time tearing
down camp give us
attention so uh so it's my hope
that there's going to be some burning
man for you to taste tomorrow
and the next night it's called maybe
like a mini dock until we're able to
come back together in the dust thanks
everyone for being here
uh this is
thanks everyone make some friends uh
this was one of my most profound burns
so thank you all but it's been really
tremendous as